Guide to the George A. Clark Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
George A. Clark papers
1897-1917
SC0229
Clark, George A. (George Archibald), 1865-1918.
1 Linear feet
Correspondence, articles, clippings and other materials pertaining to Clark's controversial study of sealing in the Pribilof Islands, Alaska. These papers primarily concern the studies done between 1909-1913 and focus on Clark's dispute with Henry Wood Elliott's findings. Correspondents include A. H. Proctor, Mrs. Minnie Maddern Fiske, Barton W. Evermann, Henry W. Elliott, David Starr Jordan, Mary C. Dickerson, Charles K. Field, and Bird McGuire. Other subjects include administrative issues, Clark's attempts to have his reports and articles published, and analysis of problems resulting from the government's actions. Collection also includes "The Fur Seals of the Pribilof Islands: Report of the Special Investigation, 1912"; a translation by Marie de Koroleff of a portion of Bishop Veniaminov's account of the Russian method of conducting the fur-seal industry (1840); and a transcript of the Treasury Hearing with Henry W. Elliott, April 15, 1897.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Philip C. Clark, 1980.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
George A. Clark, born in Eden Prairie, Minnesota in 1864, graduated from the University of Minnesota and served as Academic Secretary of Stanford University from 1891-1918. He was Secretary of the Bering Sea Fur Seal Commission (1896-1898) and was involved in the special investigation of seal herds for the Bureau of Fisheries in 1909 and 1912. He died 27 April 1918.
Description of the Collection
Correspondence, articles, clippings and other materials pertaining to Clark's controversial study of sealing in the Pribilof Islands, Alaska. These papers primarily concern the studies done between 1909-1913 and focus on Clark's dispute with Henry Wood Elliott's findings. Correspondents include A. H. Proctor, Mrs. Minnie Maddern Fiske, Barton W. Evermann, Henry W. Elliott, David Starr Jordan, Mary C. Dickerson, Charles K. Field, and Bird McGuire. Other subjects include administrative issues, Clark's attempts to have his reports and articles published, and analysis of problems resulting from the government's actions. Collection also includes "The Fur Seals of the Pribilof Islands: Report of the Special Investigation, 1912"; a translation by Marie de Koroleff of a portion of Bishop Veniaminov's account of the Russian method of conducting the fur-seal industry (1840); and a transcript of the Treasury Hearing with Henry W. Elliott, April 15, 1897.
Access Terms
Clark, George A. (George Archibald), 1865-1918.; Dickerson, Mary Cynthia, 1866-; Elliott, Henry Wood, 1846-1930.; Evermann, Barton Warren, 1853-1932.; Field, Charles K., (Charles Kellogg), 1873-1948.; Fiske, Minnie Maddern, 1865-1932.; Jordan, David Starr, 1851-1931; McGuire, Bird Segle, 1865-1930.; Proctor, A. H.; Pribilof Islands (Alaska); Sealing --Alaska.
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - Correspondence, 1909-10 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, May-July 1913 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, Aug.-Sept. 1913 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, October 1913 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letter in response to Elliott’s report [missing pages after p. 35], Oct. 16, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, November 1913 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, December 1913 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, January 1914 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, Feb.-March 1914 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, April-May 1914 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, June 1-13, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, June 15-30, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, July 1914 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Unsigned correspondence to Prof. Slonaker, Sept. 1914 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, Sept.-Oct. 1914 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1915-17 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Bills and receipts (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Clark, “Law Versus Common Sense as Applied to the Fur Seals”, circa June 1914 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - “The Deadly Parallel” [presumably by Elliott], 1913 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - “Governmental Mismanagement of Fur Seals” [presumably by Clark] (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous covers to letters (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Publications and clippings (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Publications not on fur seals (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - The Fur Seals of the Pribilof Islands—Report of Special Investigation 1912. Section I-III (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Report. Section IV-VI (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Report. Section VII-IX (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Report. Section X (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Russian method of conducting the fur-seal industry 1805-1840, translated by Miss Marie de Koroleff [found with January 1914 correspondence] (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Short-hand article, 1913 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Treasury Hearing [transcript], Henry W. Elliott, April 15, 1897 (Box 2, Folder 14)